Guide to the Shearith Israel Congregation records, 1921-2002 MS 738
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Shearith Israel Congregation collection
1921-2002
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Unknown; Denn, Meyer; Franklin, Wayne; Marvins, Libby; Marvins, Edward
MS 738
3.5 Linear Feet 6 boxes
.04 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0738aip_001 (.04 GB)
The collection contains six boxes of correspondence, event materials (including programs, correspondence, and memorabilia), newsletters, bulletins, news clippings, books, photographs, financial documents, sermons, and video and audio material of events that document the history of Shearith Israel Congregation in Wharton, Texas, from 1921 to 2002.
Biographical / Historical
Shearith Israel Congregation had its inception in 1899 when the Jewish citizens of Wharton, Texas, first met to conduct religious services, using members' homes as meeting places. Later, under the leadership of I. Ditch, a congregation was organized and Sabbath services were held each Friday night and Saturday morning in the lower floor of the old Masonic Lodge Building. The first Torah used by the congregation was ordered from New York by Mr. Ditch.
As the community grew and the number of Jewish families increased plans were formulated for the building of a Synagogue. A committee composed of Joe Schwartz, Ben Davis, T. Gordon, and M. Bernstein solicited funds and the Synagogue was built on the corner of Rusk and Burleson streets in 1921. The officers of the Congregation at that time were: Ben Davis, President; Joe Schwartz, Vice President; A. M. Smith, Treasurer; Herman Davis, Secretary; Trustees, T. Gordon, M. Levine, I. Kurtz, and L. Smith. In addition to the officers the congregation listed as members the following: J. Goldman, B. Leder, P. Alpard, L. Abovitz, S. Yarno, M. Berstein, D. Gordon, I. Kreitstein, and J. Abovitz.
At first the membership consisted mainly of Wharton citizens, but as the Jewish population increased in surrounding towns the congregation expanded to include those who lived nearby from El Campo, Bay City, Ganado, Edna, Palacios, and Richmond, making a total of 85 members. In 1940, President Ben Davis headed a committee to build the Jewish Community Center. A tract of 2.14 acres was purchased and the building was completed in the fall of 1940. It was located just off the Bay City Highway near the city park.
Rabbi Israel Rosenberg came to Wharton to assume the pulpit of Shearith Israel in 1955, and remained the community's spiritual leader until 1978. A year after Rosenberg's arrival, the community dedicated a new, state-of-the-art synagogue building in the shape of a six-pointed Star of David at 1821 Old Lane City Rd., that was designed by Houston Jewish architect, Lenard Gabert. The construction of a Religious School building and the Maynard Smith Memorial Library followed in 1961. Perhaps, the most notable and enduring feature of the property, however, was the barbecue pit. Shearith Israel's annual barbecue fundraiser, the social event of the year for the community, attracted hundreds of Jews and non-Jews from the area, as well as relatives and former members, who descended upon Wharton to eat chicken and coleslaw.
The synagogue closed its doors in 2002, when membership dwindled from a peak of 400 members down to just 39, and sold its facilities. In 2010, the main building burned to the ground, and, besides the community hall that still stands, visitors to the site today will see nothing but a concrete slab where the sanctuary and school once stood.
Excerpts from:
"History of Shearith Israel," Box 5, folder 10 and http://jhvonline.com/remnant-of-israel-saving-jewish-history-in-wharton-and-bay-city-p24684-313.htm
Scope and Contents
Six boxes of correspondence, programs and other event materials, books, newsletters, news clippings, bulletins, photographs, sermons, memorabilia, and video (VHS) and audio recordings document the history of, and activities at, Shearith Israel Congregation in Wharton, Texas, from 1921 to 2002. Of particular interest is the Parachet (Ark curtain) that was used in the Synagogue until it closed in 2002, video of the 75th anniversary banquet, photographs of the now destroyed Synagogue's interior and exterior including from the groundbreaking ceremony in 1956 and photographs from the last service at Shearith Israel in 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from Meyer Denn via Josh Furman, March 12, 2018. Gift from Wayne Franklin, August 1, 2018. Gift from Libby and Edward Marvins, April 25, 2018
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in eight series as follows:
Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Event Materials; Series III: Media; Series IV: Memorabilia; Series V: Organization Records/Materials; Series VI: Photographic Materials Series VII: Publications/Newsletters/Bulletins Series VIII: Sermons
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
personal correspondence; clippings (information artifacts); memorabilia; programs (documents); Negatives (Photographs); photographs; books; sermons; financial records; videotapes
Subjects (Persons)
Denn, Meyer; Franklin, Wayne; Marvins, Libby; Marvins, Edward
- Series I: Correspondence, 1935-2002
  - Joe Schwartz papers, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - United Palestine Appeal/United Jewish Appeal, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Julius Ginsberg, Lodge #836 re: Nazi concentration camps and assistance for European Jews, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Silver Jubilee, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rabbi Israel Rosenberg regarding his employment at Shearith Israel, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ruthe Winegarten regarding permission to use photos in book, "Deep in the Heart: The Lives and Legends of Texas Jews", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dissolution of Shearith Israel, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Event Materials, 1945-1992
  - USO - National Jewish Welfare Board Recognition Awards program, 1945-12-16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sunday & Hebrew School Building dedication, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Building dedication/cornerstone, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Confirmation services programs, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Jubilee journal, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - A celebration of Israel's twentieth anniversary, 1968-04-28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beth David Center dedication, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Diamond Jubilee, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Shearith Israel Barbecue, 1992-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Skits and songs by Gertrude Denn (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series III: Media, ca. 1960s; 1988
  - Audio recording of (Bernard or Steven) Denn's Bar Mitvah at Shearith Israel, c. 1962 or 1965 (Box 1)
  - 75th anniversary banquet, Shearith Israel Synagogue, VHS, 1988-09-03 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Memorabilia, 1988-1992
  - Head coverings (kippot) Diamond Jubilee celebration (2), 1988 (Box 2, Envelope 1)
  - Commemorative napkin, Diamond Jubilee celebration, 1988 (Box 2, Envelope 2)
  - "I Survived the Shearith Israel Barbecue" t-shirt, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Israel Rosenberg photo block, n.d. (Box 2)
  - "Parochet" - Ark curtain from Sherith Israel Synagogue, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Seal embosser, n.d. (Box 4)
- Series V: Organization records/materials, 1936-1988
  - Shearith Israel Congregation financial ledger, 1956-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Shearith Israel Congregation financial records, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - B'nai B'rith Lodge #835 financial records, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - B'nai B'rith Lodge #835 Fundraising, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - HIAS Immigrant Bank, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - B'nai Brith Lodge #835 meeting minutes, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Shearith Israel constitution and by-laws, 1939; 1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Shearith Israel general knowledge exam, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Requirements for marriage, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "A History of Wharton Community" and "History of Shearith Israel", 1938; 1988 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Photographic Materials, 1921-1988
  - Photographs of Shearith Israel Synagogue, including groundbreaking (37), 1921-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Golden Jubilee negatives (2), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Slides (120) - Shearith Israel 's Synagogue 75th Anniversary (1901-1988), 1988-09-03 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (40) of Bay City Jewish Community Center (torn down in 1982) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Photographic negatives - Bay City Jewish Community Center, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Oversize photographs (2) of Rabbi Israel Rosenberg and Services at Shearith Israel, Franklin, Wayne (Box 2)
    Franklin, Wayne
- Series VII: Publications/Newsletters/Bulletins, 1921-2002
  - The Colorado, vol. 1, Wharton High School yearbook, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The Colorado, Wharton High School yearbook, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The Tiger, Wharton High School yearbook, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Wolozin's Catalog ("Parochet" - Ark curtain photo #40, see box 5), 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Shearith Israel bulletins, 1943-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hit Parader magazine, Vol. 3 #1, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1953-2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Shearith Israel Congregation Yearbook, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Yeda'tikha be-shem" by Rabbi Israel Rosenberg (published posthumously), 1976 (Box 6)
  - "Shay Agnon's World of Mystery and Allegory: And Analysis of Iddo and Aynam" by Rabbi Israel Rosenberg, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Shearith Israel bulletins, 1985-1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Excerpt from "The Jews in America", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Beth Yeshurun newsletter welcoming former members of Shearith Israel Congregation, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Sermons, 1963-1974
  - "The Righteous Perished" by Rabbi Israel Rosenberg (memorial address for John Fitzgerald Kennedy), 1963-11-25 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Rabbi Israel Rosenberg's sermons, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series IX: Addenda, 2002
  - Family photographs (7), 1919-1948 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of final service at Shearith Israel (13), 2002 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Tapestry Gala - invitation and program, 2011-05-03 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Invitation to "We Fought Too: Jewish Solders in America's Wars", 2011-07-14 (Box 6, Folder 14)